动物王朝第01季第05集
DynastiesS01E05
老虎是体型最大  最威武
Tigers are the largest, most powerful,
或许也是最受人喜爱的大型猫科动物
and perhaps the most loved of all the big cats.
然而在过去的一个世纪里
Yet, over the past century,
老虎的数量减少了百分之九十五
20世纪初虎的数量约有10万只
而现在世界自然基金会估计全球仅存3890只虎
their numbers have declined by 95%.
我们的团队花费两年时间
Our team has spent two years
追踪一只母虎和它的幼崽
following one tigress with her cubs
记录它养育幼崽的过程
as she attempts to rear them.
它面临的挑战不仅源于自然
Her problems come not just from the natural world,
更源于生存在人类附近
but from having to do so at close quarters with us.
位于印度中心的班达迦老虎保护区
Bandhavgarh Tiger Reserve in the heart of India.
这里是一片富足的热带丛林
A rich, tropical jungle.
在这个悬崖脚下
At the base of this cliff,
有一个秘密洞穴
a secret cave
里面藏着
hiding within
一只名叫拉吉贝拉的母虎
is a tigress known as Raj Bera
两周前  它在这个洞穴
Two weeks ago, she chose this cave
产下新的家庭成员
in which to give birth to her new family.
这是它的女儿  比芭
This is her daughter, Biba.
这是它摇摇晃晃踏出的最初几步
And these are her first, rather unsteady steps.
比芭有三个兄弟
Biba has three brothers.
四只幼崽
The four of them together
是这个老虎王朝的下一代
are the next generation of this tiger dynasty.
拉吉贝拉是地球上最强大的捕食者之一
Raj Bera is one of the most formidable predators on earth.
但它的幼崽在接下来的两年时间里
But her cubs are vulnerable and will remain so
都十分脆弱
for the next two years.
作为母亲  它要尽其所能发挥本领
It will take all her strength and skill as a mother
保护并养育幼崽
to protect and provide for them,
才能将它们抚养到成年
if she is to raise them to adulthood.
虎
这片森林有老虎家庭生活所需的一切
This forest has everything a tiger family needs.
充足的淡水
Plenty of fresh water,
可供藏身的密集灌木
dense thickets for concealment,
还有遍布猎物的开阔草原
and open grasslands full of prey.
在巢穴中与幼崽挨过饥肠辘辘的两周之后
After two hungry weeks confined to the den with her cubs,
拉吉贝拉需要食物
Raj Bera needs food.
它是个经验丰富的猎手
She is an experienced hunter.
但它的猎物时刻保持高度警觉
But her prey are always on high alert.
幸好  它知道如何隐藏踪迹
Fortunately, she knows how to disappear.
尽管经验丰富
Even with her experience,
多数狩猎都会如此收场
most hunts end this way.
但现在它面临一个两难困境
But now she faces a dilemma.
夜幕开始降临
As evening draws in,
把幼崽独自留在巢穴
leaving the cubs unprotected in their den
可能招致危险
could put them in danger.
夜行捕食者已徘徊在外
The night shift are already on the prowl.
一头懒熊
A sloth bear.
如果发现幼崽  它会将其猎杀
It will kill cubs if it can ﬁnd them.
巢穴一旦被发现  就不再安全
Once a den has been discovered, it’s no longer safe.
它需要搬家
She needs to move her family.
迁至新巢后全家安全
The family are safe at a new den.
像拉吉贝拉这样经验丰富的母虎
An experienced tigress like Raj Bera
可能知道数个像这样的藏匿处
may know half a dozen hideaways like this.
尽管它捕猎失败
Even though she failed in her hunt,
幼崽依然渴望它的乳汁
the cubs are as hungry for milk as ever.
养育并保护多达四只幼崽
For a tigress to feed and protect,
对于母虎来说是严峻的挑战
as many as four young is a relentless challenge.
它不太可能将所有幼崽都养大
It's unlikely that she will be able to raise them all.
而如今在印度
And in India today,
新的压力使抚养幼崽至成年
there are new pressures, making it harder than ever
变得前所未有的艰难
to rear a family to adulthood.
拉吉贝拉的领地面积刚好够它养育幼崽
Raj Bera's territory is just big enough to support her cubs,
拉吉贝拉
但它被其它老虎的领地包围
but she's surrounded by territories held by other tigers.
而整个保护区被人类居住区环绕
And all are encircled by human settlement.
班达迦老虎保护区
班达迦共有约八十只老虎
There are about 80 tigers in Bandhavgarh.
密度高得非比寻常
This is an unusually high density.
对于生存空间的竞争十分激烈
Competition for space is intense.
脸上的伤疤是对手间争斗的证明
Scarred faces are evidence of battles between rivals.
为了保证领地安全
To keep her territory secure,
拉吉贝拉定期在长达十九千米的边界巡逻
Raj Bera regularly patrols its 12-mile-long boundary.
它每次喷尿  都是在标记
Each time she sprays, she's marking a line
其它老虎不得逾越的界线
that other tigers know they cross at their peril.
耐着正午的酷热标记领地十分辛苦
Territory marking in the midday heat is hard work.
它需要降温
She needs to cool off.
一只多情的雄孔雀
An amorous male peacock.
每一天
Every day,
它都在三项任务间取得近乎不可能的平衡
she has to strike an almost impossible balance,
分配时间进行捕猎
dividing her time between hunting,
对领地边界进行气味标记
scent marking her boundaries,
以及照料幼崽
and nursing her cubs.
目前  幼崽的需求必须优先满足
For now the demands of her young family must take precedence.
它的幼崽已成长到开始探索的阶段
Her cubs have reached the stage when they start exploring.
尽管它们仍未完全学会走路
Although even walking hasn't been completely mastered.
幼崽之间的差异逐渐显现
Differences between the cubs are beginning to appear.
三个兄弟忙着打闹
The three brothers are caught up in a rough and tumble.
但它们的姐妹比芭  踌躇退缩
But their sister, Biba, holds back.
它体型较小  也不如它的兄弟强壮
She is smaller and not as strong as her brothers.
这些差异只会随着它们的成长
And these differences will only become more apparent,
变得愈发明显
as they grow older.
两个月后
Two months later
老虎一家永远地离开了巢穴
and the family has left the den for good.
幼崽现已足够强壮  能跟上母亲
The cubs are now strong enough to follow their mother.
母虎必须开始教育幼崽了
She must now start on their education.
它带它们巡视领地
She shows them around her territory.
更重要的是  带它们品尝一种新食物
And most importantly, introduces them to a new diet.
肉
Meat.
幼崽的体型长大了一倍
The cubs have doubled in size,
所以它必须更频繁地狩猎
so that she has to hunt even more frequently
来满足它们日益增长的胃口
to provide for their growing appetites.
自从它的幼崽出生
Since the birth of her cubs,
拉吉贝拉便无法像过去那样
Raj Bera has not been able to patrol her territory
定期巡逻领地
as regularly as she did.
这使对手有机可乘
And that has given a rival an opportunity.
这是索萝
This is Solo,
拉吉贝拉的成年女儿
Raj Bera's adult daughter.
它擅自闯入了母亲的领土
And she is trespassing on her mother's lands,
整个班达迦最富饶的地方之一
some of the richest in the whole of Bandhavgarh.
它或许不知道拉吉贝拉在这里狩猎
She may be unaware that Raj Bera is hunting here.
通常成年老虎会相互避开
Normally adult tigers avoid each other.
因为即便是母女打斗也有可能致命
Because ﬁghts even between mother and daughter can be fatal.
不过目前  索萝似乎是在试探它的母亲
But now, Solo appears to be testing her mother.
面对拉吉贝拉稳操胜券的步伐
Faced with Raj Bera's confident advance,
索萝立刻表现出顺从
Solo immediately defers,
像幼崽一样露出腹部
rolling on her back like a cub.
它还不够成熟  不够强壮
She's not old enough or strong enough
难以争夺领土
to challenge for the territory...
暂时不能
Yet.
拉吉贝拉仍然是这里的统治者
Raj Bera is still the ruler here.
但是索萝发出了警告
But Solo has issued a warning.
领土重归安全
With their territory secure,
全家得以一起放松
the family can relax together.
幼崽现在把越来越多的时间
The cubs are now spending more and more time
用在锻炼协调性和灵活性上
developing their coordination and agility.
它们从游戏中学习
And they do that through play.
一头野猪
A wild boar.
它可能是成年老虎菜单上的美味
It could be on the menu of an adult tiger.
但其中一只幼年公虎有点急功近利
But one of the male cubs is being a little ambitious.
还是等等吧
Perhaps not yet.
班达迦的冬季降临
Winter arrives in Bandhavgarh.
幼崽九个月大了
The cubs are nine months old.
步入了青春期
In their adolescence.
邻居开始对它们更加提防
And the neighbours are beginning to take them more seriously.
目前拉吉贝拉顺利让它的幼崽都活了下来
Raj Bera has done well to keep all her cubs alive so far.
一般只有百分之五十的幼崽
Typically only 50% of tiger cubs
能幸存到成年
survive to adulthood.
不过现在  家庭关系开始改变
But now, the family relationships are changing.
它不再让幼崽先吃
She no longer lets the cubs eat first.
它必须让它们明白总有一天
She has to teach them that one day
它们需要自力更生
they will have to provide for themselves.
等它饱食餍足
Once she has had her fill,
它的儿子占据尸体
her sons dominate the carcass.
只有等它们吃完
It's only when they have finished
体型较小的女儿  比芭
that their smaller sister, Biba,
才能不受打扰地进食
gets her chance to feed undisturbed.
警报提示有入侵者
Alarm calls warn of an intruder.
这次是一只成年公虎
This time it's an adult male tiger.
它的体型比拉吉贝拉大三分之一  更加强壮
He‘s a third bigger than Raj Bera and much more powerful.
这是幼崽最喜欢的水洼
This is the cubs' favourite water hole.
母亲和儿子
Mother and sons
饭后小憩
sleep off their meal.
但比芭独自离开
But Biba heads off alone.
成年公虎有时会杀死幼崽
Adult male tigers sometimes kill cubs,
所以接近一只公虎风险极高
so, to approach one is a huge risk.
当然  除非它是你的父亲
Unless of course he's your father,
森林里唯一不会伤害它的公虎
the only male in the forest who would never harm her.
公虎很少见到自己的后代
Tiger fathers rarely meet their offspring.
它似乎也不想跟女儿熟络
And he doesn't seem keen to get acquainted.
但是只要它在森林里巡逻
But while he is patrolling the forest,
其它公虎就会绕道而行
other males will keep away.
幼崽就是安全的
And the cubs will be safe.
至于其它的一切  幼崽依赖拉吉贝拉照料
For everything else, the cubs depend on Raj Bera.
它仍然需要供养整个家庭
She still has to provide for the whole family.
夏季到来
It's summer.
接下来的几周  灼热的高温
Over the next few weeks the searing heat
将会吸干这片土地上的水分
will suck the moisture from the land.
气温骤升  超过四十五摄氏度
Temperatures soar to over 45 degrees.
班达迦必须承受十年来最严重的干旱
And Bandhavgarh has to endure the worst drought in a decade.
这是秃鹫的好时机
It's a good time to be a vulture.
拉吉贝拉领地里的水洼
The water holes in Raj Bera's territory
吸引着保护区干渴难耐的居民
become magnets for the park's thirsty inhabitants.
通常  叶猴大部分时间
Normally, langurs spend most of their time
都在遥不可及的树上
out of reach in the trees.
但干旱期间
But during the drought,
它们必须冒险穿过开阔地带去喝水
they must risk crossing open ground to get water.
一旦勇敢的成年叶猴开始行动
Once the braver adults make their move,
剩下的成员便紧随其后
the rest of the troop follow.
离开安乐窝  它们紧张不安
Out of their comfort zone, they're nervous.
这里没有危险
No danger here,
至少在它看来
as far as she can see.
但是你不可能在喝水的同时观望四周
But you can't drink and watch all at the same time.
在拉吉贝拉的领土中心
Here in the heart of Raj Bera’s territory,
这些水洼成了旱季期间
these water holes become the focus of the family's life
家庭生活的焦点
throughout these driest months.
被吸引至水洼的不只有猎物
It's not just prey that are drawn here to the water holes.
新的入侵者
A new trespasser.
看来这只母虎今天不打算宣告主权
It seems this tigress is weary of pressing her claim today.
但是很显然现在有
But it's clear there are now
更多的对手觊觎拉吉贝拉的狩猎领地
more rivals for Raj Bera's hunting territory.
现在遥远的嚎叫预示着以后的麻烦
And now distant roars signal further trouble.
索萝  拉吉贝拉的成年女儿
Solo, Raj Bera's adult daughter,
正在进行第一次交配
is mating for the first time.
很快它会产下需要喂养的幼崽
She will soon have her own family with new mouths to feed.
那时离它回来就不远了
And it‘s not long before she's back,
在它母亲的领地深处狩猎
hunting deep in her mother's territory.
它在偷猎
She is poaching.
一岁大的幼崽需要互相
The year-old cubs are practising their hunting skills
磨练捕猎技术
on each other.
捕捉猎物需要力量和敏捷
Capturing prey requires power and agility.
同时还需伏击和攻击的能力
As well as the skills of ambush and attack.
为了生存它们需要掌握猎杀技巧
Their survival will depend on mastering the ability to kill.
但在未来的八个月里
But for another eight months,
母亲依然要继续喂养它们
their mother must continue to provide.
她捕猎的工作量也大大增加
And she's having to work much harder now.
即使是这般大小的猎物
Even a kill as big as this
也只够全家吃几天
won't last the family more than a couple of days.
它的儿子们先进食
Her sons are the first to every meal
并小心翼翼守护着自己那份食物
and jealously guard their share.
比芭只能等待
Biba is forced to wait.
倘若还剩零星碎肉就已经很幸运了
She will be lucky if she gets anything more than scraps.
离开它吃饱了的兄弟们
Leaving her well-fed brothers behind,
比芭试图自己捕猎
Biba tries to hunt for herself.
它已看过母亲多次示范
She's watched her mother do this many times.
跟踪猎物
Stalk,
并俯身
and drop.
它已经掌握了隐身技术
She has mastered the technique of becoming invisible.
但它的体型和力量都还不足以发起突袭
But she doesn't yet have the size or strength to strike.
强风预示着雨季的来临
Strong winds signal the arrival of the monsoon.
对多数居住在森林里的动物来说
The abundance of water means that,
充沛的水源意味着
for most of the forest's inhabitants,
好时节又回来了
the good times have returned.
但雨季对拉吉贝拉一家来说是最坏的季节
But the monsoon is the worst time for Raj Bera and her family.
它的猎物不再依赖于水洼
Her prey are no longer dependent on the water holes.
而是可以在它的领地里四散生活
They are now free to disperse throughout her territory.
这使伏击变得难上加难
They will be much harder for her to ambush.
几周后  在它领地的西界附近
A few weeks later near the western boundary of her lands,
发生了一场打斗
there has been a fight.
拉吉贝拉不幸负伤
And Raj Bera is injured.
母虎严重负伤
A serious injury to a mother tiger
意味着它的幼崽会挨饿
can mean starvation for her cubs.
比芭总是最后一个
Biba is invariably the last
享用母亲狩猎成果的孩子
to benefit from her mother's hunting.
它急需自力更生
She needs to fend for herself.
为此它必须找到属于自己的领地
And to do that, she must find her own territory,
远离它的兄弟
away from her brothers.
但它能去哪呢
But where can she go?
其他的领地早已被占领
Every other territory is already occupied.
它只能被迫离开班达迦向外搜寻
She's forced to search outside Bandhavgarh altogether.
它母亲也会与它永别
Her mother will never see her again.
雄性幼崽也饥肠辘辘
The male cubs are also going hungry.
它们也在试着自力更生
They, too, are trying to fend for themselves.
对于新手来说  鹿太过警觉
The deer are too alert for novices.
有三只嗷嗷待哺的青年雄性幼崽
With the demands of three adolescent male cubs
再加上它对手日渐增长的敌意
and increasing hostility from her rivals,
拉吉贝拉面临自己的王朝有史以来最大的威胁
Raj Bera is facing the greatest ever threat to her dynasty.
它迈了一大步
She takes a drastic step
离开安全的公园  希望找到更易捕猎之物
and leaves the safety of the park in the hope of easier prey.
邻近村庄的牛
Cattle in the neighbouring villages.
雌虎与人类之间一直存在冲突
For tigress and people, there is real danger here.
而且拉吉贝拉无法战胜对方
It's a conflict that Raj Bera cannot win.
次日黎明时分
Dawn, the next day.
拉吉贝拉
Raj Bera.
被公园工作人员解救
She was rescued by the park authorities
并重新回到自己的领地
and released back into her territory,
一家团聚
to rejoin her family.
过去两年里
Over the last two years,
它含辛茹苦养育自己的幼崽长大
she's struggled to raise her cubs safely to this point.
尽管失去了女儿
And although she's lost her daughter,
但它的儿子即将成年
her sons are on the brink of adulthood.
排除万难
Against the odds,
它仍有机会为自己的老虎王朝
she still has the chance to secure the future
提供一个美好的未来
of her tiger dynasty.
动物王朝
拍摄现场
一百年前  世界上老虎总数逾十万
A century ago, there were more than 100,000 tigers.
而如今  仅存四千只
Today, there are only 4,000,
其中七成生活在印度
with 70% of them found in India,
大部分在诸如班达迦这样的保护区
mostly in protected areas such as Bandhavgarh.
像克里蒂·卡兰斯这样的印度自然保护者
Indian conservationists like Krithi Karanth
对这些保护区面临的挑战感到担忧
are concerned about the challenges facing these reserves.
不像非洲和美洲的公园
Unlike parks in Africa and the Americas,
克里蒂·卡兰斯
野生老虎保护者
印度的公园面积非常小
parks in India are extremely small.
因此老虎种群在这些小园区生存压力巨大
So tiger populations in these tiny parks are under huge pressure.
很有可能在不久的将来
There is a real danger
这种美丽神奇的猫科动物会灭绝
that we could see this amazing cat go extinct.
班达迦里居住着八十多只老虎
Bandhavgarh is home to over 80 tigers.
但是园区负责人西奥·韦伯发现
But, as director Theo Webb discovers,
想发现老虎的踪迹并不容易
they're not easy to find.
西奥·韦伯
园区负责人
我刚以为看见了老虎  结果发现是堆红沙
I just saw a tiger which turned out to be red sand.
我今天犯蠢了
I'm the stupid one today.
即使是货真价实的老虎也很难被发现
Even the real thing is almost invisible.
这就是我们找不到老虎的原因
So, right here is one of the problems why we can't find tigers,
因为它们隐藏得太好
because they are so well hidden.
如果你仔细看那里
If you look in here,
它们的伪装很厉害
they are so well camouflaged,
尤其是在这茂密的灌木丛中
especially in this dense undergrowth.
它身上的条纹与竹子融于一体
Her stripes blend in exactly with the bamboo.
想看到它们几乎不可能
It's almost impossible to see them.
当地向导告诉拍摄团队
Local guides have told the crew
有一只叫拉吉贝拉的雌虎即将产下幼崽
of a tigress they call Raj Bera who is expecting cubs.
如果他们能找到它
If they can find her,
它将会是完美的跟拍对象
she will be the perfect tiger to follow.
向导听着其它动物的警报信号
The guides listen for other animals' warning calls.
猴子跳来跳去
Monkey leaping along.
这表明老虎就在那里
That's a sign that the tiger's, like, right there.
好的
Okay.
摄制组得以追踪老虎的动向
The team can then home in on the tiger.
我们刚刚遇见了这头雌虎
So we've just come across this tigress.
我们听到了警报信号  跟着它来到这里
We heard alarm calls, followed her here,
它可能正是我们一直在找的那只雌虎
and it could be our female that we've been looking for.
我们将两张照片做了比较
We've done a comparison between two photos,
我们知道一张照片里是它
one we know is her,
我刚拍下另一张它的照片  看上去很相似
and one of her I took just now. They're looking similar.
-应该就是它  -是的
- It's pretty much her. - Yeah.
它是拉吉贝拉
It's Raj Bera.
但它的虎穴在哪呢
But where is her den?
雌虎会选择
A tigress will choose
不易接近的地方生产
the most inaccessible place to give birth.
用车辆无法追踪
Impossible to follow in a vehicle.
森林部门用大象
But the forest department have elephants
来帮助保护动物免遭偷猎者袭击
to help protect the animals against poachers.
他们在巡逻的同时也在找寻虎穴
And while patrolling the forest, they also search for dens.
两周后  拉吉贝拉的虎穴被发现
Two weeks later, Raj Bera's den has been discovered.
它选择了
She's chosen one of
整座公园中最难以进入的地方
the most inaccessible spots in the whole park,
来做巢穴  从老虎的角度来说相当明智
to make her den, which is kinda sensible if you're a tiger.
现在他们需要在不打扰老虎一家的情况下
Now they need to film the family
拍摄它们
without disturbing them.
摄影师约翰·布朗在虎穴外放置了
Cameraman, John Brown, positions a remote controlled camera
一台远程遥控摄相机
away from the den.
这只特别设计的三角架使约翰
The specially designed tripod allows John
能撤到更远处  将打扰降至最低
to retreat even further to minimise disturbance.
他终于捕捉到了极其罕见的景象
He's finally rewarded with an extremely rare view.
只有几周大的幼崽
Cubs just a few weeks old.
约翰·布朗
摄影师
今天真是太不可思议了
Today's been absolutely incredible.
我们从一个极其独特的角度
We've had a completely unique view
看到了老虎的生活
into the life of tigers.
这是我职业生涯中最棒的时刻之一
It's been one of the most amazing moments of my career.
我从没想到我们真的能拍到
I never thought we'd get it actually,
不过  我没有跟其他人这么说
but, you know... I didn't tell anyone else that.
一旦幼崽离巢
Once the cubs leave the den,
老虎一家就隐没在森林中
the family disappears into the forest.
现在摄制组要换一种新的手段
Now the crew have to switch to a new technique.
这是被公园管理部门
Camera traps,
常规使用的感应式相机
used regularly by the park authorities.
他们监视像水坑这种动物可能出现的地点
They stake out likely locations including water holes.
许多栖居于森林中的动物出现了
Plenty of the forest's inhabitants tum up.
但没有老虎
But no tigers.
几周后  西奥发现
A few weeks later, Theo discovers
其中一台感应相机不知为何被淹了
that one of the camera traps has somehow become flooded.
天哪
Oh, my God.
谜团解开了
Mystery solved.
终于  拍到了幼崽的近距离影像
And, at last, intimate shots of the cubs.
最终甚至拍到了它们的父亲
And eventually even of their father.
接下来九个月中
For another nine months,
随着幼崽长大  摄制组得以追踪
the crew are able to follow the life of the family
老虎一家的生活
as the cubs grow up.
但突然间
But then, suddenly,
他们目睹了故事非常不同的另一面
they witness a very different side to the story.
我们追踪的雌虎在那边
So, somewhere over here is our tigress.
为了寻找食物
In order to find food,
它来到这些非常危险的区域
she's coming to these really risky areas,
来捕猎牛  狗  任何它能找到的食物
to hunt cattle, dogs, whatever she can find.
所以这对它来说是很大的惊吓
So, this is really scary for her.
说实话  对我们来说也是
And to be honest, for us as well.
在八十公里内没有其它的老虎保护区
There is no other tiger reserve within 50 miles.
所以不管老虎何时走出公园
So, whenever a tiger leaves the park,
它都不可避免会遇到人类
it's inevitable that it will encounter people.
森林部门接管了此事
The forest department take control.
拉吉贝拉被注射镇静剂
Raj Bera is tranquillised,
并被带至安全地带
and taken to safety.
第二天  它回到了自己的领地
And, next day, is returned to her territory.
我们拍摄这只雌虎已有两年时间
We've been filming this female for two years
我们对它已产生感情
and we've got attached to her.
我们看到它和那些两周大的幼崽
You know, we've seen her with these two-week-old cubs.
我们看到它失去其中一只
We've seen her lose one cub,
现在我们看到它走出公园
and now we've seen her outside the park.
这就是一只现代老虎的生活
This is the life of a modern tiger.
这并不容易  和它们过去的生活不同
It's not easy. It's not how it used to be for them.
我们需要创造更多空间
We need to create more space
让老虎繁衍生息
for tigers to move, breed, and disperse.
我们有责任确保
It is our responsibility to make sure
子孙后代  也包括我自己的
that future generations of children, including my own,
能够在野外看到老虎
get to see tigers in the wild.
我们在这部纪录片中看到的所有动物
All the animals we've seen in this series
都需要自己的生存空间
need space in which to live.
空间的减少对它们的生存造成巨大威胁
And loss of space is a great threat to their survival
事实上对所有其它物种也一样
as it is to virtually all other species.
我们人类自己  作为一类物种
We ourselves, one single species,
已经占据了这座星球上
have taken over vast tracts
宜居部分的广阔土地
of the habitable surface of the planet.
毫无疑问  我们应该容许其它生灵
Surely, we should allow those other creatures
与我们共享这颗星球
we share the planet with,
保有它们那一部分的古老传统
to retain some part of their ancient heritage.